react is fantastic for large projects
but for small projects you might want to
use something like HTM X it's a very
simple way to add interactivity to a web
page let's go into Astro and figure out
exactly what htx is and how to translate
your react skills into this new world of
[Music]
htx all right this is the simple test
application that we're going to build
that's going to show you all the core
mechanics of htx now we're going to
start off with this page example right
here at the top you click on the
different pages and you load dynamically
the data of each one of those pages into
that table let's get going to start off
with we have an empty Aster application
on the left-and side and the browser on
the right hand side first thing we need
to do is add HTM X to our project the
first thing we're going to add is HTM
x.org yes that is the actual package
name of htx and then we're going to add
Astro htx Astro htx is just a simple
integration that just injects that HTM X
onto our Astro page now over in our
Astro configuration I'm just going to
bring in that Astro htx and then I'm
going to bring it into our
Integrations and that's it now we can
use HTM X anywhere we want to in the
site so the first thing I'll do is bring
in some HTML right at the top here we
got our page example then we got our
page links you can just click on them
right now they just go to Hash which
means the same page now down at the
bottom we have an empty content div
that's where we're going to put the
contents of that table and it's got an
ID contents and that's how we're going
to reference that so the first htx
primitive we're going to learn is hxg
hxg just says to htx when you click on
that link go and perform a get operation
and then you give it the URL in this
case it's going to that URL is going to
be/ partials /list with a page and that
page is going to be the page that they
clicked on then you want to give it a
Target where do I put that so we're
going to go and take that output from
that partials list and then put it
somewhere well we're going to put it
we're going to put it in Contents and we
do that by using hash contents so we
give it any kind of query selector to go
and find it in this case that's an ID
contents and that's going to go and take
that output and put it in that contents
div but of course now when you click on
one of those that HX git which is going
to/ partial /list is getting a 404
because there's no partials list so
let's go create that so in the Pages
directory I'm going to create a new file
partials list. asro and within that I'm
just going to put a div that tells us
what page we clicked
on how cool is that super easy now there
is one thing you've got to watch out for
here and let's go take a look at our
inspector to see what that is so as I
click on each of these we can see that
we're getting the page if we click on
that we can see that we get a full
response and that full response has
everything in it and what we really want
is just the HTML for that div so the way
to make that happen in Astro is to
Define it as a partial making that
happen is as simple as adding partial
equals true and now we get back just the
div that we want now to make this real
we have some fake user data over in our
slash
components and we also have a user list
Astro component that just takes that
data and formats it so let's go bring in
both of those to our list partial and
we'll make page a local we'll make sure
that it's a number and it's defaulted to
one and then we'll go use that user list
to just take our data and slice it so we
get the first page of our users save try
again and wow that is really cool now
one thing I don't like is it doesn't
start by showing you the first page so
let's go make that happen so go back
over here to our index we'll bring in
that
partial and then just drop it in here
for our contents now we get our first
page automatically
and as we click through we get the
additional
Pages how easy is that you can see why
people are really stoked about HT Max
now let's take a look at HTM X triggers
by creating a search field in HTM X it's
really easy you're going to love it all
right let's go add the HTML for our
search box right up at the top we have a
horizontal rule as well as a H1 with our
search example and then we've got our
input field and finally our div where
we're going to put our search results
and so far we're just going to use hxg
with partial search which we don't have
yet and then HX Target to Target that
search results so let's go build our
search
route just like before we're going to
bring in the users and the user list but
this time we're going to get the search
parameter and then we're going to go and
filter that list based on that search
otherwise it's basically the same thing
let's hit save and we'll try it out so
let's search for particular
value now in order to make it actually
make that HX skit we have to blur the
field so let's hit Tab and now we get
our HX git but that's not particularly
great right we wanted to search as we
type and then debounce it so how do we
do that well we use HX trigger for that
we can say that we want a trigger which
is the key up when things have changed
and then we want a delay of 500
milliseconds and that's our debounce let
H save try it
again and there you go Dynamic search
how easy is that so a core premise of
HTM X is HTML as an engine of
application State and we've been doing a
little bit of State Management so far
for example our de balance search what
happens if you want to do something like
say a counter how do we do a counter in
HDMX let's go create a new partial
called counter and into there I'll bring
some HTML now this HTML is going to have
a form with an ID of counter and it's
going to have an HX post not HX git in
this case post so we do post and it's
going to go to partials counter which is
where this is and then we're going to
have a hidden value for our count and
then a button that submits and then also
lists our count so at this point it's
going to say zero all the time because
we don't actually increment that value
yet so let's go bring this into our
page so now we got our counter component
let's go bring this in at the
bottom now when we click on it we're not
actually incrementing but there are
actually form posts going to the server
so what we need to do is get the current
count we had from the form data and then
just increment it see what
happens so we'll get our form data and
then we'll just get the count out of
that and then increment it by
one all right let's try again and now
we've got an incrementer awesome but
what happens if you want to click on a
button and update multiple places on the
page can you do that with HJ Maxx sure
you can there's a thing called out of
bounds swap so let's go take a look at
how to implement that first thing we
need to do is put another counter on the
page that we can update so right up at
the top here we'll say we have something
like a
header and that header has another
counter in it so let's hit save and see
where that goes that goes up here get
zero
cool and we get this div ID with another
counter so when we click on the
increment down here we want to see both
of these get updated well how do we do
that let's go over and counter and then
we'll say that we have another div with
the ID another counter and then we'll
use HX swap oob so HX swap means Swap
this HTML and oob means out of band
which means that it's not contained as
part of this fragment so let's hit save
and see what happens well what happens
is we get a zero down here which is not
great and then we increment it we
increment all of those we're
incrementing this value here we
incrementing that one up there so is
there a way to make sure that we don't
get that initial div here so we don't
have two another counters well it's
pretty easy all you need to do is just
say well on the first one we don't want
to Output it so we'll just put a check
in there for
count and there we go now when we click
increment we increment both the local
counter as well as the counter in the
header so if you got something like an
e-commerce system where when you click
on add to cart you want the little cart
count up in the header change this is
going to make that happen for you all
right now all this code is available to
you for free on GitHub and a link in the
description right down below and there
are two more things that I want to show
you to really get you excited about HG
Max the first is to compare this to a
react implementation so in that same
GitHub repo is a react version that has
all the stuff we've come to know and
love about react use State use effect
everything is done on the client let's
go take a look at how this looks in the
browser so the react version is on the
left the HTM X that we just did is on
the right and you can click and get the
react back version and of course the big
difference here is what's actually
happening over the wire so as we click
we can see the Json data coming in and
that and that Json data is of course
Json so everything that's required to
actually render all of that Json onto
the screen is Javascript that has to
come along with the page so how much
does all that JavaScript actually weigh
well when I hit Refresh on a built
version of this it's about 145k worth of
JavaScript if we take a look at the same
thing over in
htx the amount of JavaScript is about
49k and that would be absolutely limited
so you're never going to get beyond that
initial 49k as you add more components
and more complexity just going to stick
at that 49k because that 49k is all
that's required to do all of the
conceivable HDMX that you'd want to do
for your entire application and of
course as a thanks to you for watching
this channel there's also in that same
directory an htx movies app that takes
all of the stuff that we've just learned
about HJ Max and turns it into a cool
movie app sitting on top of the movie
database well I hope you enjoyed this
quick look at hmx I hope you're as
excited about it as I am I also do a lot
of react and xjs stuff as well different
tools for different applications you
want to go check out my course on nextjs
it's Pro nextjs dodev there's an
excellent State Management tutorial up
there already subscribe today and of
course if you like this video hit that
like button if you really like the video
hit the Subscribe button and click on
that Bell you'll be notified the next
time a new blue collar coder comes out